<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the bringing in of any commodities traded by the Eastland Merchants into this kingdome, aswell by subiects as strangers, not free of that company with a publication of certaine statutes for the restraint of all His Maiesties subiects from shipping any commodities in strangers bottomes, either into, or out of this kingdome.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1622-07-21</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836754</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836754</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1040</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1040)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1601:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King. A proclamation prohibiting the bringing in of any commodities traded by the Eastland Merchants into this kingdome, aswell by subiects as strangers, not free of that company with a publication of certaine statutes for the restraint of all His Maiesties subiects from shipping any commodities in strangers bottomes, either into, or out of this kingdome.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1622-07-21</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Bonham Norton, and Iohn Bill, printers to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXII. [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Theobalds, the one and twentieth day of Iuly, in the twentieth yeere of our reigne ..</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eastland Company --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Restraint of trade --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:1040:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ A Proclamation prohibiting the bringing in of any Commodities traded by the Eaſtland Merchants into this Kingdome, aſwell by ſubiects as ſtrangers, not free of that Company; with a publication of certaine Statutes for the reſtraint of all His Maieſties ſubiects from ſhipping any commodities in ſtrangers bottomes, either into, or out of this Kingdome.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a great part of our Princely care, to maintaine and increaſe the</hi> trade of Our Merchants, and the ſtrength of Our nauy, The one being as the Veines whereby wealth is imported into Our eſtate, and the other as principall ſinewes for the ſtrength and ſeruice of Our Crowne and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Whereas therefore the ſociety and Company of Our Caſtland Merchants, trading the Balticke Seas, haue by the ſpace of forty yeeres paſt, at the leaſt, had a ſetled and conſtant poſſeſſion of trade in thoſe parts, and haue had the ſole bringing in of all the commodities of thoſe countries, as namely, Hempe, Flaxe, Dot-aſhes, Soape aſhes, Poloma wooll, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, Yearne, Eaſtland linnen cloth, Pitch, Tarre and Wood, whereby Our Kingdome hath beene much enriched, Our ſhippes and Matriners ſet on worke, and the honour and fame of Our Nation and Kingdome ſpread and enlarged in thoſe parts: And whereas, for further encouragement, the ſayd Company haue had and enioyed by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents, vnder the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> in the time of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> priuiledge for the ſole bringing in of the ſayd commodities, with generall prohibitions and reſtraints of others not licenſed and authoriſed by the ſayd Letters Patents, to traffique or trade contrary to the tenor of the ſame letters Patents; We, minding the vpholding and continuance of the ſayd trade, and not to ſuffer that the ſayd ſociety ſhall ſuſtaine any violation or diminution of their liberties and priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Haue thought good to ratifie and publiſh vnto all perſons, aſwell ſubiects as ſtrangers, the ſaid priuiledges and reſtraints, to the end that none of them preſume to attempt any thing againſt the ſame: And doe heereby ſtraitely charge and command all Our Cuſtomers, Comptrollers, and all other Our Officers at the Ports, and alſo the Farmers of Our Cuſtomes and their Deputies and Wayters, That they ſuffer not any hempe, flaxe, pot-aſhes, ſoape-aſhes, Poloma wooll, cordage, yarne, Eaſtland Imnen cloth, pitch, carre, or wood, nor any other commodities whatſoeuer, brought from any the forraine parts or regions wherein the ſayd Company haue vſed to trade, to be landed, except onely ſuch as ſhall be brought in by ſuch as are free of the ſaid Company: Prouided alwaies, that the importation of corne and graine be left free and without reſtraint: Any thing heerein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, whereas there hath beene in ancient time diuers good and politicke Lawes, made againſt the ſhipping of merchandiſes in ſtrangers bottomes, either inward or outward, as namely the Statutes of <hi>5. Richardi 2.4. Henrici 7.32. Henrici 8. &amp;c.</hi> which Lawes of latter yeeres haue beene much neglected, to the great preiudice of the nauigation of Our kingdome; Wee doe ſtraitely charge and command, that the ſayd Lawes be from hencefoorth duly put in execution, vpon the paines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contayned, and vpon payne of Our high indignation and diſpleaſure towards all Our Officers and Miniſters, which ſhall be found ſlacke and remiſſe in procuring and aſſiſting the due execution of the ſayd Lawes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Our Court at Theobalds, <date>the one and twentieth day of Iuly, in the twentieth yeere of Our Reigne of England, France, and Ireland, and of Scotland the ſixe and fiftieth.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by <hi>BONHAM NORTON,</hi> and <hi>IOHN BILL,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. M.DC.XXII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
